Some people hear their own
inner voices
with great clearness
and they live
by what they hear
Such people become crazy
or they become legend
Tristan Ludlow was born
in the Moon of the Falling Leaves
It was a terrible winter
His mother almost died
bringing him into this world
His father, the Colonel,
brought him to me
I wrapped him in a bearskin
and held him all that night
As he grew into a man
I taught him the great joy
of the kill
when the hunter
cuts out its warm heart
and holds it in his hands
setting its spirit free
Colonel Ludlow had three sons
but Tristan was his favorite
I had had sons too
But they were gone now
forever
It was a very bad time
The Colonel had tried
to help the People
but it was no use
So he decided
to go his own way
He wanted to lose the madness
over the mountains, he said
and begin again
"Lose the madness, '"he said
And so we lived for many years
and the boys grew strong
Alfred was the older brother
old even for his years
Samuel was the youngest
There was nothing these brothers
would not do for him
They watched over him
like a treasure
One year...
I am an old man
and cannot remember the year
But it was the Moon
of the Red Grass
when Isabel Ludlow,
their mother
went away for the winter
She said the winters
were too cruel for her
She said she was afraid
of the bears
She was a strange woman anyway
That spring, though,
she did not return
And, after that,
she did not come much to see us
Alfred wrote her many letters
but Tristan refused
to speak of her
His world was here with me
Every warrior hopes a good death
will find him
but Tristan couldn't wait
He went looking for his
Tristan!
Here
- Was it a bear?
- Yes, sir
- Can you breathe?
- Yes
Take your hand away
Take it away
You're a stupid,
half-brained jackass
- Yes, sir
- One Stab put you up to this?
You deserve to be dead
God knows how you've
lived so long
It'll be all right, son
I have these letters
many letters
Read them
They are from all of them
Ludlow
Isabel
Samuel
the whole family
the whole story
It is all written here
April 13, 1913
Dear Isabel:
I am not fool enough to try
to reorder a life already lived
but I fear I have not done well raising
our sons alone in this wild place
What did I know of children?
I was trained to lead men
This is infinitely harder
Dear William:
You take too much responsibility
on yourself, as always
Our sons are finding their own paths
They are willful, certainly,
but then
who are you and I
to complain of willfulness?
As for Samuel,
I have big news
At a Harvard tea
for Amy Lowell
he met and instantly loved
Miss Susannah Finncannon
I know it will
surprise you greatly
but they are engaged
He will bring her to Montana
this summer to meet his brothers
and you
So, William,
please behave yourself
and be as charming
as only you can be
There he is
- How the hell are you?
- Good And you?
- Samuel Good to see you, boy
- Father, how are you?
- Good to see you
- Hello
This is my fiancée, Susannah
- Miss Finncannon
- Nice to meet you
- It's an honor
- This is Alfred
- How do you do?
- Here's your dog, miss
- Thank you
- It's a horse
- That's a strange-looking animal
This is Finn
He's a champion
You like exotic-looking dogs then,
Miss Finncannon?
Very much, Mr. Ludlow
- Please call me Susannah
- All right
- He's just plain old Alfred
- Shut up
- Where's Tristan?
- He's off somewhere You know him
He'll welcome you home tonight
or I'll know the reason why
Miss Finncannon, please
Did you have a good journey?
She is such a lovely creature
But I fear the loss
of her parents
has given her
a certain fragility
I think she feels very alone
in the world
But she has found a new family now,
hasn't she?
The German military is ready
to use chaos in Croatia
as a justification for actions that could
plunge the entire civilized world into...
The word "civilized" has no place
in discussing the affairs of this world
Mother told us of your sympathy
for the social reformers
You make it sound like a disease
No, I'm in agreement
You mother told me all about One Stab
She says he was a great warrior
Yes
He has a bag of scalps
to prove it
But don't worry
He's devoted to Father now
Rather, they're devoted
to each other
Can he speak English?
Stab, speak English?
He wouldn't lower himself
to speak English
But watch out because
he understands it perfectly well
There's Tristan
- Don't they feed you?
- Not much
- You smell
- Miss me, did you?
- Still hung over?
- Still drunk
Isn't she amazing?
So this is Tristan
And does he speak English?
For God's sake
Miss Finncannon,
it's a pleasure to meet you
I hope you and Ugly here
find every happiness together
Don't mind my brother Your dog
has more breeding than he has
This is Mother's room
It's lovely
- It's a pleasure to meet you, Pet
- And you, miss
Thank you
- Which one?
- It's this one
Angelica Susannah
Hello
You must be Isabel Two
I've already met your mother
and father
- How old are you?
- Thirteen
When I was 13,
I was sent away
to boarding school
I hated it
May I help you?
You're going to marry Samuel
That's right, I am
I'm going to marry Tristan
We'll be sisters
I see you two have met
Isabel Two is letting me help
Would you like a rest?
You must be exhausted
No, not at all
This is so refreshing
all this grandeur,
this unexpected
gift from God
It doesn't seem like much of a gift
in a hard winter, I assure you
Where's Samuel?
Inside I could tell your father
wanted him all to himself
- You're very generous
- No, just happy
Stop mooning over her
and come in here
Samuel wants to know
about those calves from Cheyenne
Get in here
Please excuse my father
It makes him feel young and powerful
to treat us like we're idiot children
For all His countless blessings,
may God's holy name be praised Amen
Tell Father what you were saying
about Vienna
- What's that?
- It's the Kaiser
He won't stop them
from annihilating Serbia
Let's not talk about war, please
Susannah hears
that England's mobilizing
We're stuck out here
while all this is going on
- Thank God
- You wouldn't want us to evade a duty
- Wouldn't I?
- Father, with respect...
Please excuse me
for being late
I packed so carefully,
I couldn't find anything
Thank you
Would you like some...
As evening fell
a maiden stood
At the edge of a wood
In her hands lay the reins
Of a stallion
And n'er I'd seen
A girl as fair
Heard a gentler voice anywhere
Whispered, alas
She belonged
Belonged to another
Another, forever
Yes, she belonged to
The twilight and mist
Dear Isabel:
How strange to have a cultivated woman
in the house again
and how intoxicating
To have all three of my sons
under my roof again
fills me with such a deep,
quiet satisfaction
that I thank God
There's a friend of yours
A dollar says
he brings her back
Whoa
Easy
You got it
Nice work
You guys look
like ice cream cones
I know you would have
Ready Here we go
Go easy on him, Susannah
Alfred, you take over
I must talk to Tristan
You've disgraced the Colonel's name
- Nice shiner
- I hit her back
She's got me spinning
I'll bet
She's got these ideas
and theories, and she's so...
What?
Nothing
How'd you break the mare?
She's what?
She's sort of passionate
- She a virgin?
- Good Lord, Tristan
- You brought it up
- Of course she is
Are you?
- Yes, I am
- Going to wait till you're married?
See, she says...
Susannah thinks that...
We're not gonna wait
And you're afraid
you won't meet her expectations?
I guess I am
Sort of I don't know
Should I be?
Samuel, God bless you
You are good
at everything you try
I'm sure it will be the same
with fucking
Tristan, really
- She's my future wife
- You're not going to fuck her?
I'm planning to be with her
I recommend fucking
- You're impossible
- You brought it up
My point!
Good morning,
Colonel Ludlow
Tristan's hunting
He didn't do it
You don't have to worry
about Tristan
Meet John T and James O'Banion
They own the mercantile store
- Morning, James, John T, Sheriff
- Morning, Alfred
We're looking for a man we heard
might be in this part of the country
Name is Tom Cullen
Here's a likeness
What did this fella do?
Do you recognize him?
- Yeah, I recognize him
- We got him
This fellow passed by here
maybe four or five years ago
Did some work here
on his way to San Francisco
He was hoping to book passage
to Australia
Or Hong Kong
I can't remember
- Can you remember?
- Hong Kong
- What is he wanted for?
- He...
That would be
of a private nature
"Private nature"?
It's a public office you hold, Sheriff
Gentlemen
"There came a low hiss,
a horrid sound
that made Rikki Tikki Tavi
jump back two clear feet
And then out of the grass
rose up the head
and spread hood of Nag
the big black cobra"
I can read another story
The Germans broke through
at Armentieres
The British are trapped
in the Belgian lowlands
- This paper is a week old!
- Calm down
With my fluent German,
I could become an officer
And lead other boys to the slaughter
and be slaughtered yourself
The men who served under you
worshipped you
They were all damn fools
This is a turning point
in history
- How can we...
- What?
You can't expect us not to
be part of this
- You taught us...
- To think for yourselves
- And to defend what's ours
- Yes, what is ours!
We've already lost two cousins
Who we've never met! Don't talk at me
as though I've never seen a war!
Not a war like this
They said that about the War
of Secession and the Indian wars
They say it to sell newspapers
These are not the Indian wars
We're fighting against naked aggression!
There will be no more talk of wars
in this house! Damn it!
I'm sorry, Susannah
I'm going to Canada to enlist
I'm going with him
I'm sorry, my love
I meant to speak to you tonight
I know you'll understand
It's the only honorable thing to do
What's that?
It's a book my father wrote
to try to convince the government
to alter their policies
towards the Indians
in the Dakotas
Samuel won't change his mind
Change it for him
What happened between them?
Father says
she never liked it here
I think they loved mostly the idea
of each other
Don't let him go
I'll take care of him
October 14, 1914
My dear Isabel:
Today our sons are leaving home
to defend an England
they have never seen
I am unable to stop them
I have tried to shelter our sons
from all the madness
and now they go to seek it
Be careful
You don't have to go
Good-bye
Don't worry, Father
Take care
I'll bring you
the Kaiser's helmet
Bring yourself back
That would please me more
Yes, sir
- Take care of Samuel
- I will
Colonel Ludlow told me:
"Ride with them to Calgary
Bring back the horses '"
"Damn fools, '"he called them
The Colonel
would not have his sons
ride off to war
on old nags
damn fools or not
Let's join them
Bring your plate
He'll be back
May we join you?
Sit down
Feeling lonely in there
Sit here
What's her name, Two?
Lady Tristan's Lady
In the story,
Tristan's lady was Isolde
- Do you know who Isolde was?
- No
Your daughter needs an education
She can read and write, Colonel
School might be awkward for her
- I'll teach her myself
- May I help?
Yeah I'll teach her
history and mathematics
With your permission, Decker,
and yours, Pet
What do you think?
What will she do
with all this education?
She'll live a richer,
fuller life, of course
She's a half-breed
Not in this house
- Tristan calls me a half-breed
- Tristan calls you a half-breed?
He says I'm half gopher
and half hawk
- After her chores
- Yeah
- To us all
- To you, sir
- And miss
- And to the boys
And the boys
Get back to your unit
Those boys are boring
I'd rather have you
watching my back
Now, mate
February 3, 1915
Dear Susannah:
The horror of this place
is indescribable
Nothing is
as I thought it would be
Keep your distance!
Keep your spacing!
Tonight, as I prayed for the souls
of those who've died so terribly
yet so bravely
I admit that I also prayed
for personal glory
Is that wrong to want
to distinguish myself gloriously
in combat as my father did?
Tristan and Alfred
watch over me so carefully
I may never get the opportunity
Charge!
Alfred! Are you all right?
Goddamn it!
- Are you hit?
- It's just a scratch
Susannah, I see now
not that my father was right,
but that I was naive
- Let me up, damn it!
- Stay down!
Fall back!
Still, we place our bodies
in God's keeping
We go into battle honorably
full of confidence
with His name on our lips
- We're pinned here
- We'll wait
- Give him a hand
- Help him down
Goddamn
Susannah:
I try to guard against despair
but there are moments when it seems
that all human decency is broken down
Alfred will recover
from his wounds
but he and Tristan seem
to have drifted apart, or worse
I cannot understand it
I miss you more
than you can imagine
You are all that is clean
and cool and pure
I close my eyes
and fix my thoughts on you
I now regret that we listened
to everyone and agreed to wait to marry
Even more, I regret that I left
before we could be together
as we planned, my beloved
Please stay on at the ranch
and wait for me
Don't let Father worry
I know God's mercy
will protect me
aided considerably
by Tristan
who seems to be in France
less to fight the Germans
than to act
as a nursemaid to me
Be well, my love
Your own, Samuel
Captain needs me to translate
this before tonight's reconnaissance
- Alfred will want to see you
- I'll be there
- Yeah?
- Go on
Where's Samuel?
He's translating
He'll be here
Boy, that's a good one
- Vino?
- Put that away
- They said you'll get a medal
- Yes
- They're sending me home
- I'm glad for you
I'm an officer
I belong with my men
Horseshit
What's left of them
MacKenzie was just brought in
His leg's turned bad
- He said...
- What?
What is it?
He said your brother volunteered
to take his place
on the reconnaissance
with the Capitan
Goddamn it!
I told you to stay with him!
- I'm here!
- Where? I can't see
I can't move!
I'm coming!
I got you now
I got you
You're doing good
We're going home
God, no!
Goddamn you, God!
Tristan, it's me
March 20, 1915
Dear Father and Susannah:
I am being discharged from the Army,
but I cannot come home yet
I will write to Grandfather Ludlow
in Cornwall
and ask him to let me join him
and go to sea
As for our beloved Samuel
all I can send home
is his heart
Alfred will bring it back
He should be buried
up in the box canyon
where he used
to draw the birds
Your son, Tristan
He certainly was the best
of all of us, wasn't he?
Good night
What you saw
before Samuel left...
Please, don't...
No, I want to
It is Samuel I loved
All right
Tristan will be back someday
Your father will be pleased
Susannah was to return to Boston
on the morning train
but a norther blew
for three days
and drifted over the tracks
The Colonel insisted
she stay on until spring
The house was too empty,
he said
This was still her home,
he told her
He should have let her go
But how could he have known
what would happen?
She was not to blame
She was like the water
that freezes in the rock
and splits it apart
It was no more her fault
than it is the fault of the water
when the rock shatters
You know how much l...
You know how much
I loved Samuel
And I think you know...
Out of respect for him,
I wanted to say it in this place
I think you know that
I'm in love with you
From the first moment
I saw you
like in a novel
That's my mother's overblown
romantic imagination coming out in me
You're not making this
very easy for me
Sorry
Is there any hope
that you could learn to love me?
Not the way you love Samuel,
of course
but enough to...
We could make a life together
A happy life
I don't think so
Sounds like you're not sure, though
Maybe there's a chance?
- What?
- I can only cause you pain, Alfred
Why don't you let me
be the judge of that?
I didn't break it,
but I can fix it
I can put the damn wheel back on
and take it off myself
Go take a nap
- What?
- Look!
I'm going into town if...
Welcome home, son
I couldn't save him
Of course you couldn't
It's all right
Have a nice ride today?
Excuse me, Father
Tristan, please
When are you planning
to be married?
Good morning
Damn you
You will marry her
- Make an honest woman of her?
- Yes!
God damn you to hell
Yes, I will marry her,
if she'll have me
If she'll have you?
Do you love her?
Or did you seduce her
just to spite me?
That's not what I did
- What about Samuel?
- What?
You tell me about Samuel
We all loved Samuel
Samuel is dead What?
How convenient for you
Because you love her,
I will forgive you for that
Once You say that again,
and we're not brothers
Once!
You know you can't make her happy
I'm gonna try
You will fail
I'll be leaving today
I wish you both all the best
- Good-bye, son
- Wish me luck
Good luck
September 7, 1915
Dearest Mother:
I think I may have found
my place in this world
Helena is a city
turned modern overnight
bursting with all the energy
and vitality
of our times
I feel alive here
There is much opportunity
for anyone
willing to dedicate himself
to his labors
Already, I have acquired a reputation
for honesty and fair dealing
and I am pleased to call some of
Helena's most influential citizens
my friends
They are determined to see
this city grow, as am I
We're proud of you
Mother, thank you
for your kind letter
You knew my hopes
That you understand my disappointment
is a great comfort to me
Every night I pray for the grace
to forgive Tristan
I know you understand
Your loving son, Alfred
Quit it!
Goddamn it!
If we have a boy,
I'd like to call him Samuel
And if it's a girl, Isabel
I'll still love you
You'll tolerate me
because of how much I love you
Nothing
I heard from your mother
She says Alfred has hooked up
with those damn O'Banion brothers
- He's doing well
- Alfred's gonna do well wherever he is
- Except here with us
- That's my fault
- I didn't say that
- Couldn't save Samuel either, could I?
Don't you dare say that
That was in God's hands
Was it?
Colonel! Lost a couple calves
near Camas Canyon
- Might be a grizzly
- My grizzly?
- You take him, Tristan
- Damn right I will
I don't know why Tristan
did not kill that damn old bear
The Old Ones say:
"When a man and an animal
have spilled each other's blood
they become one '"
I said four beers,
Mr. Sachtleben
And I said no Indians
- He's quite civilized, I assure you
- Yeah?
- Give him a beer
- Stay out of it
- My father said four
- He heard me
We're about to reach an understanding
Just give him a goddamn beer!
Stay out of it!
Damn you
You're a damn fool
You're spoiling for a fight
with a man who outweighs you
As we speak, he's searching
for some kind of a weapon
Isn't that right?
To split your stupid skull
and kill you and good riddance
Leave it!
- Yes, sir?
- I want four beers, now
The lousy owner says
he doesn't want to serve Indians
Get back
Do you see this man?
Do you?
His name is One Stab
He's a venerated elder of the Cree and has
counted coup on hundreds of his enemies
He is our friend
He's thirsty
I think it was the bear's voice
he heard deep inside him
growling low
of dark, secret places
Were you going to say good-bye?
How long will you be gone?
Not long
A few months
I can make it better for you
If we'd had a child
or if I were pregnant,
would you still go?
Yes
Just give me a chance
Don't do that
Look at me
Please, look at me
I'll wait for you
However long it takes
I'll wait for you forever
Will he come back?
I don't know I don't know
Stab says yes
April 20, 1918
Dear Tristan:
It has been months now,
and still no word
The only sign
that you are alive
is a tattered parcel that arrived today
from New Guinea
covered with strange writing
and containing what appears to be
a native bracelet
Meant for me, I presume
But perhaps not
Do you still care to know
what is happening here?
Cattle prices continue to fall
and winter seems never ending
Why don't you write?
Are you never coming back
and afraid to tell me?
Alfred continues to do well
His business has expanded to include
financial concerns in Chicago
and Washington
I don't pretend to understand
He wants us to send Isabel Two
to boarding school in Chicago
but she adamantly refuses
to leave the ranch
I think she, too,
is waiting for you
I have nowhere
to send this letter
and no reason to believe
you wish to receive it
I write it only for myself
I will hide it away with all the things
left unsaid and undone
between us
December 12, 1919
Dear Susannah:
I have become a hunter
Tell Stab there are creatures here
that cannot even be found in books
I have killed them all
All we had is dead
As I am dead
Marry another
Colonel, it looks like
we've got company
- I have come to ask for your blessing
- My blessing?
You see, these gentlemen and...
And a great many others,
I might add
They're urging me
to run for office
- What office?
- The United States Congress
That's how highly
we think of your son
And what do you gentlemen
hope to get out of this?
I beg your pardon?
I've spoken plain English, sir
What do you want for yourselves?
Father, I don't think
that these gentlemen...
Didn't you ask that question
or do you believe these gentlemen
back you out of patriotic duty
and your inestimable worth?
You forget yourself, Father
I am no longer a child
Colonel, the Congress...
Congress is government, sir
I worked for the government once
The issues that we...
Indians! Indians were
the issue in those days
There is nothing so grotesque
as the meeting of a child
with a bullet
or an entire village slaughtered
while sleeping
That was the government's resolution
of that particular issue
I've seen nothing since then
to persuade me it's gained
in wisdom, common sense
or humanity
Gentlemen, my father, for whom
I have the deepest respect
says that the government
has neither wisdom nor humanity
I will then consider it
my absolute duty as my father's son
to bring both wisdom and humanity
to the United States Congress
I thank you for your blessing
Gentlemen
- Gentlemen, wait for me in the cars
- Yes Certainly
Are you all right?
What's wrong?
I don't know what to say
Tristan's always been wild
- You love him for that
- Do I?
I suppose I do
He does love you
She's to be your brother's wife
Yes, though you better
remind him of that fact
He's not here
to defend himself
No, but I see you are here
to defend him and what is his
even though
he's abandoned her and you
I won't even speak
of who else he abandoned
Damn you, boy
Don't you blame my son
for Samuel's death!
Samuel chose to be a soldier,
and soldiers die
sent to their slaughter
by men in government
Parasites like you!
Damn and blast you!
Damn you
And damn you too!
Shut your mouth
Leave her out of this!
Get out of my house
and get off my land
Why? Because I want
to serve my country as you did?
Or because, like you,
I love a woman who doesn't love me?
He used her and deserted her,
your darling Tristan
Alfred, don't Please
I loved her!
I love her still
He stole her from me
If you want to know the truth
he stole her from Samuel
before the war
God help me, I'll kill you
Here
Read your darling Tristan's letter
You deserve to be happy
Late that night we found
the Colonel on the floor
beside a cold fire
He could not move
His hair turned white overnight
and he became an old man
And after that,
Tristan sent no more letters
As the years passed by
we would hear that someone
had seen him on a ship
going up some river
no white man had gone up before
Stories came to us
Strange stories
And then, for years,
there was nothing
He was lost to us
That was all we knew
But every year,
in the Moon of the Falling Leaves
I would dream that the bear's voice
inside him had grown silent
and that Tristan might again
come to live in the world
But then the winter would come
And then another spring
And still he stayed away
What the hell is he doing?
She's a mean old bitch,
but she's yours
Welcome home
Old man!
Where's Father?
He had a stroke some years ago
He can't talk now
Oh, Father
He wants to celebrate
I'm happy too
Father, this is for you
"Colonel William Ludlow,
from his son Tristan"
I didn't know
These are boars' tusks,
made by a Javanese warrior
He, too, was a great man
I have other things for Mother
and Little Izzy and Susannah
What is it?
Alfred and Miss Susannah
were married several years ago
Your brother's a congressman now
They have a big, new place
in Helena
It's as it should be
Cattle prices dropped
after the war ended
The Colonel ain't seem to care
He lost just about everything he had
We'll make it back
on horses or something else
if we have to
We'll make it back
He's saying that your brother
voted for the Volstead Act
Did he? You suggesting
I become a bootlegger?
Good money in bootlegging,
if you know what you're doing
Screw the government
Screw them
Screw them!
Screw the government
Forever turned out
to be too long
I know
Here
I don't want it
They told me
that this was magic
that whoever wore it
would be protected
Keep it
Don't you want to see Alfred?
It's probably better
that I don't
Tell him hello
and congratulations
He likes you
Welcome home
Isabel?
I want you to have him
I have something for you too
I brought it back
It's from lerapetra
- That's in...
- Crete
- Yeah
- I know where it is
Your father taught me
European history
A little girl
That's me, right?
Thank you
Okay, we'll see you
in a few days
Don't wait on me
I'll be fine
It was then that Tristan came
into the quiet heart
of his life
The bear inside him was sleeping
It is hard to tell
of happiness
Time goes by
and we feel safe too soon
- I heard the oddest news
- Yes?
Yes
Tristan
is back
Yes, I know
You know?
How do you know?
I saw him
He had the audacity
to come here just to see you?
He wanted to see you,
but thought you'd get upset
He might be right
What did he...
What did he say?
He said to say hello
and congratulations
Silly me
He told you the news?
What do you think?
Come on
It's perfectly absurd
Marrying Isabel Two
God, she's practically our sister
She can't be more than,
what, 19?
Twenty
I can't imagine what the hell
Decker is thinking of
to allow this
Perhaps he's thinking
of his daughter's happiness
Happiness?
With Tristan?
You, of all people,
should know how impossible that is
I'm not Isabel Two
June 2, 1921
Dear Tristan:
I was so pleased to hear
of your coming marriage
Your father must be very happy
Isabel Two is like
a daughter to him
as she was named
after your own mother
It seems as though it was always
meant to be, doesn't it?
Damnation
Samuel Decker Ludlow
Dearest Tristan:
Alfred and I were delighted
to hear of your son's birth
We hoped for a child of our own,
but of that I despair
I know Alfred thinks of you often
I look forward to the day when we
all might see one another again
Your son bears a proud
and noble name
I know he will live up to it
Please give my love
to Isabel Two
and to your father
and everyone else
Yours always, Susannah
Evening, gentlemen
Been meaning to talk to you
about one or two things
By all means
As you know perfectly well
we handle the liquor around here
Now, you've been
a small-time operator
An amateur, frankly
Lately, your shipments
have been getting a little fat
and my patience
has been getting a little thin
So the next time
you get in our way
will be the last time
Excuse me
I appreciate it
Perhaps you're wondering
why you're not dead already
Because your brother
is Congressman Ludlow
And that's it
That's all
Kenneth Thomas
Can't you just say hello?
- Hello, Alfred
- Hello, Tristan
- Who's this young man?
- This is Samuel
She's beautiful
Let me see
- Who is this lady?
- I'm your Aunt Susannah
I used to know your Uncle Samuel
who died in the war
- You look like him
- That's what Grandpa says
He was very brave and very good
Grandpa says that too
Grandpa says I can have
Uncle Samuel's gun when I'm bigger
Would you come and see it?
I'd love to
Sometime
- He's a fine boy
- He is
- How is Father? Well?
- As well as can be expected
- I wish...
- Pardon the intrusion
Excuse me
We're ready for your speech now
I'll be there in a minute
Thank you
- We'll meet again soon?
- I'd like that
Watch this
Go and get Tynert
I think you missed a bump, Stab
Jesus!
Sir, we have information
that you're transporting goods
in violation
of the Volstead Act
If you mean a case of Irish whiskey
for my father, I am
Give it up
He'll be disappointed
Hold him down
Let's get out of here
- There's an envelope in his pocket
- Now
My brother told you
to stay out of our way
Put him in the car
- I don't want to see him
- Father...
I don't want to see him
I'm so very sorry
Father won't see me, even now?
He blames the government
for Isabel's...
There's something
we have to talk about
The officer you beat
almost died
Now, everyone understands
but you'll have to plead guilty
serve 30 days
And the one who shot his gun?
He was
reprimanded
- The O'Banions?
- Nothing
You have to let it go
It was a terrible, tragic accident
Listen to me
You let this go now
You got in over your head
I'll need a minute
I'm so sorry
We all loved her
How are you?
I'm fine
We never get to see you
I gave a speech the other day
- You did?
- Yes
My first public engagement
It was on the responsibilities
of women in...
It's good to see you
I'm sorry
I still sometimes dream
that I'm the mother
of your children
I wanted her to die
Maybe I even wanted Samuel to die
You had nothing to do
with Samuel's death
And you had nothing to do
with Isabel's death
Didn't I?
Go home
Go home to Alfred
Where were you?
I just went out for a walk
I needed a walk
What are you doing home?
Your doctor rang,
said you missed your appointment
I called home
You weren't here l...
I feel very tired
I'm going to bed
You have won her
I am bringing her home
Alfred
I followed all the rules:
Man's and God's
And you...
You followed none of them
And they all loved you more
Samuel, Father
and even my own wife
I'd like a moment
alone with her
When Samuel died...
When Samuel died, I cursed God
And I damn everybody around me
as well as myself
You are not damned
I won't allow that
You're not damned!
Samuel,
this is a gentleman's gun
It's smaller,
but it's just as powerful
That's what you want
when you grow up, isn't it? A gun
Samuel, come here!
Run along now Go with Pet
Get him in the house
He's a fine boy
You know we're not here
to arrest you
You take me to the woods
I don't want my boy to see
Let's get on with it
- Father
- Colonel Ludlow, sir
What's going on here?
You don't have to be a genius to know
they'll come after you for this
Yeah
Yeah?
I want to ask you
to watch over my children
Watch over Samuel
Brother, it would be an honor
How much I wanted
to take scalps
but it was not my kill
That night,
we buried the bodies
and dumped the car in a deep pool
in the upper Missouri
I remember when he was a boy
I thought Tristan would never live
to be an old man
I was wrong about that
I was wrong about many things
It was those who loved him most
who died young
He was a rock
they broke themselves against
however much
he tried to protect them
But he had his honor
and a long life
and he saw his children grow
and raise their own families
Tristan died in 1963
in the Moon of the Popping Trees
He was last seen
up in the north country
where the hunting was still good
His grave is unmarked
but it does not matter
He had always lived
in the borderland anyway:
Somewhere between this world
and the other
It was a good death
}}